Congratulations! You have imported the Hello World app and added many functionalities to it.
You have added drawables, dimens, style, menu, and test. Now it's time for you to write your own app.
Let me show you how to create an app in Android Studio. Go to File, click New, New Project.
Here you are choosing the application name and the package name.
I'm going to call my app Awesome. I own the domain sqisland.com, so I put that in my Company Domain.
Android will pick a package name for me automatically. The project location is where you want to store this
project on disk. Choose a location that you can find later. Next, we need to decide a minimum SDK.
This will affect how many devices can run your app. Click on Help me choose to get a better idea.
This is the percentage of devices that you'll be able to target it you select the corresponding level.
As of November 2015, API level 16 Jelly Bean is a good choice. Next, we will add an activity to our app.
Choose the Blank Activity. Finally, give a name to your activity.
MainActivity is fine. You can leave the rest of the parameters as the default.
First, go to the left tab and select Project view. This reflects the directory structure as on disk,
and it's a little bit easier to understand. Next, expand the app, and take a look at what is generated.
This should be pretty familiar to you by now. Just like Hello World, we have a MainActivity, and in the res
folder we see the various mipmap directories for the launcher icon.
If you go into values, you will see that we have strings and also dimens.
We have covered that in the Hello World app. With the Hello World app, you have a really good foundation to
go ahead and write your own awesome app.