Hello, this is Chiu-Ki Chan, and welcome to the Android Studio Installation module.
In this module, you are going to learn how to setup Android Studio, the IDE, or Integrated Development
Environment for Android. First, we will check that you have the proper JDK installed on your computer.
Next, we will download and install Android Studio. Finally, we will import the Hello World project and run
it on an emulator, and then a device.
Android Studio requires JDK version 7. To make sure that is installed on your computer, open the Terminal app.
If you are on Windows, you can use the command prompt. In the terminal, type java -version.
Look at the build number. The number after 1. is the JDK version.
In this example we have a 6, which means that we need to download the latest JDK.
Go to the JDK 7 download page. Scroll down to look for the one matching your operating system.
Accept the license agreement and download. Once the download completes, open the file to install it.
Then go back to the terminal. Type java -version to verify that you have JDK 7.
Once again, the number behind 1. is the JDK version. Here you can see that we have JDK 7 installed.