Hello, this is Chiu-Ki Chan, and welcome to Start Developing for Android, the Introduction module.
In this course, I'm going to explain to you how Android works, how to install Android Studio, how to write
your very first Android app, and what are the next steps to become an Android developer.
Before we write any code, I will give you a basic understanding of the Android world, what is an Android app,
and how is it organized? How do different components talk to each other?
Next we will download Android Studio, the Integrated Development Environment, or IDE for Android.
After we set up Android Studio, we will write our very first Android App, Hello World.
We will start with the bare minimum with activity, layout, strings, and manifest.
From there, we will add one concept at a time, learning about drawables, dimens, styles, and menu.
By the end of the course, you will have written your very first Android app and ready to learn more.
I will show you different topics to deepen your knowledge, and you'll be on your way to write awesome Android apps.
Let's get started.