Right now our Hello World app doesn't do much. It displays Hello world.
Let's add something so that we can interact with it. Let's add something to action bar so that you can click
on it and choose a menu item. To do that, we first need to create a menu.xml.
Go to the res folder, and create a new directory called menu. Next, we'll create a file under menu called
activity_main because we are going to use this menu in our MainActivity.
Android Studio automatically created the top note menu for you.
We are going to add an item inside it. We will give it an id/action_bye because we are going to say bye when
the user clicks on this menu item. We will also need to give it something to display.
We are going to put the string/say_bye as the title. Right now the string/say_bye doesn't exist yet.
Let's create it. Put your mouse over @string/say_bye and then Option+Return.
Android Studio will give us a choice to create the string. Now we can type the value we want, Say bye!
Now we have the menu.xml. Let's use that in our MainActivity. We will need to override the onCreate options
menu function in order to display this menu. You can type that out yourself, or you can ask Android Studio
to create that function for you. Go to Code, Override Methods.
It's a very long list of functions, so you can start typing for Android Studio to jump to the one you want to override.
The one we want is onCreateOptionsMenu. Android Studio will fill in the default for you, which is to call
the super function. Let's replace that with our own logic. We would like to inflate the menu that we just created.
To do that, you need to getMenuInflater, and then call inflate.
The first parameter is the XML that you created, so R.menu.activity_main.
The next argument is a menu object, which is given to you in the function signature.
After that, we will need to return true to tell Android that yes we have taken care of the menu here.
Let's deploy and take a look. There are three dots on the top-right corner.
That is where our menu is. If you click on it, it says Say bye!
Go ahead and click on it. The menu disappears, but then nothing happens.
Let's hook it up so that it actually does something. Go back to MainActivity, and we will override another function.
This time we will override onOptionsItemSelected. Once again, Android Studio will give us the default.
This time we're going to keep it, but add something in front of it.
We are going to check that if the item that's being clicked on is Say bye we're going to do something.
To do that, we can check the ID. The ID we have defined is action_bye.
We will change the string from Hello World to bye. After that, we'll return true to let Android know that
we have taken care of it. So how do we change the string? If you look back at our layout file, you can see
that we have a single text view, but right now we don't have a way to refer to it.
Let's add an ID to it. At the attribute android:id, and we're going to give it the id/greeting.
Now with an ID, we can change its value in our activity. To do that, we will need to locate this view using findViewByID.
What this does is to tell Android to look into that layout and find the view with this ID.
I'm casting it into a TextView because that is the type of the view that we have defined in the layout.
Android Studio is showing red right now because we have not imported TextView yet.
Go ahead and do that by pressing Option+Return. GreetingView is red because it has not been defined yet.
Let's define that as a field. Once again, Option+Return, we can select Create field greetingView,
and we will choose the type TextView. In general, Option+Return is very useful in Android Studio because
it's context sensitive and tries to suggest things that you may want to do.
Now that we have greetingView, let's change its value when the menu item is selected.
Go back to the onOptionsSelected function, and we're going to change the value of this TextView, greetingView.setText.
We are going to say bye this time, so let's type R.String.bye.
Again, bye has not been defined yet. You can use Option+Enter to define it just like before when we did it
in the XML, or you can navigate to the strings.xml and add it yourself.
Let's try that this time. To navigate to the strings.xml file, you can click on the menu on the left-hand
side, or you can use the keyboard shortcut Shift+Command+O. This will allow you to open the file name by
name, strings.xml. Let's add a new item with the ID bye. Press Command+D to duplicate the line hello_world,
change the name to bye, and the value to Goodbye. Now if you go back to MainActivity, R.string.bye is no longer read.
Let's deploy and try this out. Click on the three dots to show the menu, and then click on Say bye!
Look, the greeting has changed from Hello world to Goodbye! In summary, to add a menu to your action bar,
you need to define the menu in XML. In your menu item, define an ID so that you can refer to it and a title
so that you can show some text. Next, in your activity, override onCreateOptionsMenu to inflate this menu
so that Android will show it with your activity. You will also need to override onOptionsItemSelected so
that we can do something when the user selects this item.