Let's add some test to our Hello World app. In Android, there are two kinds of tests, pure Java tests and instrumentation tests.
Android is built on top of Java, but the Android framework provides a lot of extra functionalities.
To test those extra functionalities, such as activities, you will need to write instrumentation tests.
Because of the Android dependency, they need to be run on devices or emulators.
As a result, they tend to be a little bit slower than pure Java tests.
By pure Java tests, I mean tests that exercise the logic of your app that is written using only the standard Java functions.
Because it has no Android dependency, we can run them on the JVM, or Java Virtual Machine, on your host computer.
You do not need to deploy the app onto your device or emulator, and it is much faster.
Our Hello World app does not have any pure Java logic at this moment, so we are going to write instrumentation tests.
In particular, we will be writing
Espresso tests. Espresso is an Android testing framework written by Google.
It has a fluent API that allows you to find views, perform actions on them, and then verify the state.
Let's get started.
To use Espresso, we need to make sure that we have the support library downloaded.
Click on the little Android icon with the arrow here. Click on SDK Tools.
You can see that we have the Android Support Library, so we are ready to go.
If not, you should check the mark to download it. Next, we need to tell Android that we are going to be
using this library. To do that, we will modify the build.gradle file under app.
Add a new session called dependencies. Inside there we will add androidtestCompile and then
com.android.support.test.espresso:espresso-core:2.2.1. What does this mean?
AndroidTestCompile means that our test will need this dependency.
The string after it tells Android which exact dependency. It is from the group
com.android.support.test.espresso, and then the module, espresso-core; 2.2.1 is the version number.
We need to add one more thing. Inside the Android block, add testInstrumentationRunner,
then 'android.support.test.runner.AndroidJUnitRunner'. This is the instrumentation runner for Espresso.
Finally, we will need to change our minSdkVersion from 1 to 8. This is the minimum SDK version that we can
use Espresso with. With that, you can click on the blue Sync Now link for Android to update its dependencies.
Now that we have our dependencies set up, let's actually add a test.
To do that, we will need to add a new folder called androidTest.
Add it under the level src under app. Inside that, add a java folder.
Notice that the icon is screen. This means that Android Studio recognizes it as a test source folder.
Now go to MainActivity, and select Navigate Test. Android Studio will give us a choice to create a new test.
Let's choose that. Select JUnit4, and click OK. We're going to put a test in the directory that we just
created, app/src/androidTest/java, etc. To mark this as a test, we will use annotations.
First, annotate the class with @RunWith AndroidJUnit4.class. Next, we are going to add an Android test rule.
With this rule, Espresso will automatically launch our activity before each test method.
Right now we don't have any test methods yet, so let's add one.
We make a test method by writing a method and then annotating it with test.
Let's call it bye. Finally, after we did all the scaffolding, we can actually write our test.
We want to first verify that the TextView with the ID greeting is displaying Hello World.
To verify the initial value of our TextView, we will use onView withId to locate the view.
We are telling Espresso that we want to find this view, which has the ID greeting.
Once the view is found, we can do some verification. Add .check matches withText R.string.hello_world.
This tells Espresso to go ahead and verify that this view contains the text as defined in our strings.xml file.
It is better to check the string this way rather than hard coding the value hello world because if we want to
internationalize our app, this will automatically load the right string out of the proper resource folder.
Let's run this test. Right-click on MainActivityTest, and choose Create MainActivityTest.
This lets us create a new run configuration. Click OK, and then click the green triangle to deploy.
Android launched the app, verified the TextView, and then finishes the app.
Because it is done by a computer, it is super fast. We know that the test passed because you can see it on
the lower-left corner. There's a green circle that says OK next to the word Test Result.
Now that we know that we can run this test and it passed, let's add some more actions.
After we verify the initial state, we are going to open the action bar menu so that we can click on Say bye!
To do that, use the function openActionBarOverflowOrOptionsMenu, which takes a context.
We can get that context from the InstrumentationRegistry.getTargetContext.
This opens our menu. After that, we will click on the item that says Say bye, OnView with text R.string.say_bye.
Notice that I'm using the same withText when I was doing verification.
We can use the same matcher in verification and in also locating the view.
Once we've found the view that says say bye, we are going to click on it, .perform click.
Afterwards, we are going to verify that the TextView is changed to say bye.
Copy and paste the first line when we are looking for the greeting, and then change the string to bye.
Let's deploy and take a look. Here we go. We ran the whole test and verified that everything works.
Again, it is so fast that you can barely see the menu item expanding.
This is the advantage of writing automated testing. The machine can run it faster than you and also exactly
the same way every time. If you write tests along the way when you write your app, you can make sure that
you don't have any regressions, meaning that as you add new functionalities, the old functionalities are not broken.
In summary, there are two things you need to do to write Espresso tests.
First, you need to add the Espresso dependency in your app/build.gradle file.
Then you need to add a test to the androidTest/src/java directory.
In your test, tag the class with RunWith AndroidJUnit4, and then use the ActivityTestRule for Espresso to
launch your activity for every single test method. To make a test method, use the tag Test.
Inside your test, you can ask Espresso to find the view and then perform actions on it, or verify a state.